Sméagol!
斯米格
I've got one!
我的到了
I've got a fish, Sméag. Sméagol!
我钓到一条 斯米格 钓到了
Pull it in. Go on. Go on. Go on. Pull it in.
拉上来 快 拉呀
Déagol!
德戈
Give us that, Déagol, my love.
把它给我吧 好兄弟
Why?
为什么
Because...
因为
. it's my birthday and ! wants it.
今天是我生日 就想要
My precious.
我的宝贝
They cursed us.
他们不要我们了
Murderer.
杀人犯
"Murderer" they called us.
他们叫我们“杀人和犯”
They cursed us and drove us away.
把我们赶了出来
Gollum.
咕噜
And we wept, precious.
我们哭了 宝贝
We wept to be so alone.
我们孤苦零丁
--and cool So nice for feet
清凉又清凉
And we only wish To catch a fish
别的也不想 弄条鱼尝党
So juicy sweet
真好吃
And we forgot the taste of bread...
我们忘了面包的味道
...the sound of trees...
树的声响
...the softness of the wind.
风的温柔
We even forgot our own name.
甚至忘了我们的名字
My precious.
我的宝贝
Wake up!
醒醒
Wake up, sleepies.
懒虫 醒醒
We must go, yes.
我们该走了 听到吗
We must go at once.
我们必须马上走
Haven't you had any sleep, Mr. Frodo?
您一会儿都没睡 佛罗多老爷?
I've gone and had too much.
我睡得太久了
Must be getting late.
一定太迟了
No.
不
It isn't.
没有
It isn't midday yet.
还不到中午
The days are growing darker.
只是天色红上暗
Come on!
走啊
Must go! No time!
快走 没时间了
Not before Mr. Frodo's had something to eat.
至少让佛罗多老爷吃点东西
No time to lose, silly.
我们没时间了 来不及了 傻瓜
Here.
吃吧
What about you?
那你呢?
Oh, no, I'm not hungry. Leastways, not for lembas bread.
不 我不俄 我也不喜欢精灵人饼干
Sam.
山姆
All right.
好吧
We don't have that much left.
我们的干粮不多了
We have to be careful or we're going to run out.
得省着点吃 不然就断顿
You go ahead and eat that, Mr. Frodo.
你快吃吧 佛罗多老爷
I've rationed it.
我心里有数
There should be enough.
应该够了
For what?
够什么?
The journey home.
够回家吃的
Come, Hobbitses.
快走 起比特人
Very close now.
就快到了
Very close to Mordor.
快到魔多了
No safe places here.
此地不可入留
Hurry.
快走
I feel like I'm back at The Green Dragon...
干了一整天的活儿
... after a hard day's work.
我觉得好像回到了家乡的感觉
Only, you've never done a hard day's work.
可你从没有和干过一整天的活儿
Welcome, my lords...
诸位大人
...to Isengard!
欢迎来到艾辛格
You young rascals! A merry hunt you've led us on...
你们这俩小滑头让我们找得好音
...and now we find you feasting and...and smoking!
你们却在这儿大吃大喝还在抽烟
We are sitting on a field of victory...
我们只不过是在战场上
... enjoying a few well-earned comforts.
享受一点来之不易的胜利果实
The salted pork is particularly good.
膝猪肉的味道好极了
Salted pork?
膝猪肉?
-Hobbits. -We're under orders from Treebeard...
-震比特人 -我们现在是树胡的部下
... who's taken over management of Isengard.
他老人家已经接管了艾辛格
Young Master Gandalf.
甘道夫小少爷
I'm glad you've come.
很高兴你总算来了
Wood and water, stock and stone l can master.
树木 水 家冀和石料这些都好办
But there is a wizard to manage here...
可我还得看管那个巫师
... locked in his tower.
他就关在塔里面
And there Saruman must remain under your guard, Treebeard.
萨鲁曼还得由你继续看管 树胡
Well, let's just have his head and be done with it.
我们不如干脆把他干掉算了
No.
不
He has no power anymore.
他已经丧失了魔力
The filth of Saruman...
萨重曼的走卒
.1S washing away.
已经消灭干净
Trees will come back to live here.
树木又将回到这里生活
Young trees.
小树
-Wild trees. -Pippin!
一还有外乡的树 -皮平
Bless my bark!
我的天啊
Peregrin Took!
佩里格林 图克
I'll take that, my lad.
把它给我 孩子
Quickly, now.
快给我
Tonight we remember those who gave their blood to defend this country.
今晚我们悼念那些 为保卫这片土地而捐躯的勇士
Hail the victorious dead.
向勇士们致敬
Hail!
致敬
lam happy for you.
我真为你们高兴
He is an honorable man.
他是个可敬的人
You are both honorable men.
你们都是可敬的人
It was not Théoden of Rohan who led our people to victory.
领导罗罕人取胜的 并不是我塞奥顿王
Don't listen to me.
别在意我的话
You are young.
你很年轻
And tonight is for you.
今晚属于年轻人
Oh, you can search far and wide You can drink the whole town dry
你可以把全城的美酒喝干
But you'll never find a beer so brown
可你永远也拷不到一杯酒
As the one we drink in our hometown
能够像家乡的一样甘甜
You can drink your fancy ales You can drink 'em by the flagon
你可以把它们一口气喝完
But the only brew for the brave and true
但为勇士醒造的琼浆
Comes from The Green Dragon
只能来自绿龙客栈
Thank you! I win!
谢谢大家 我赢了
No news of Frodo?
佛罗多还没消息?
No word. Nothing.
没有消息 没有
We have time.
时间不够
Every day, Frodo moves closer to Mordor.
佛罗多正在一天天接近魔多
Do we know that?
是这样吗?
What does your heart tell you?
你有什么感觉?
That Frodo is alive.
我感觉他还活着
Yes.
没错
Yes, he's alive.
是的 他还活着
Too risky. Too risky.
太冒险了 太冒险了
Thieves.
小偷
They stole it from us.
他们偷了我们的魔戒
Kill them. Kill them. Kill them both.
字了他们 字了他们俩
Quiet! Mustn't wake them.
小声点 别吵醒他们
Mustn't ruin it now.
别坏了大事
But they knows.
可是他们知道了
They knows.
他们知道了
They suspects us.
他们在怀疑我们
What's it saying, my precious, my love?
你什么意思 亲爱的 我的宝贝?
Is Sméagol losing his nerve?
斯米格吓破胆了是吗?
No. Not.
不 没有
Never. Sméagol hates nasty Hobbitses.
不会 斯米格痛恨可恶的埠比特人
Sméagol wants to see them dead.
斯米格想让他们去死
And we will.
会有那一天
Sméagol did it once. He can do it again.
斯米格杀过人 他还可以再杀人
It's ours!
它是我们的
Ours!
我们的
We must get the precious. We must get it back.
我们要得到宝贝 要把它夺回来
Patience! Patience, my love.
耐心点 亲爱的
First we must lead them to her.
先把他们带到她那里去
We lead them to the Winding Stair.
把他们带到明虹梯
Yes, the stairs. And then?
对 蚁归梯 然后呢?
Up, up, up, up, up the stairs we go...
有由呀肘 一起往上站
...until we come to the tunnel.
一直朴向那条隧道
And when they go in...
他们一旦进去
..there's no coming out.
就别想再出来
She's always hungry.
她饥肠罚
She always needs to feed.
她时刻都要吃东西
She must eat.
吃那些脐脏的
All she gets is filthy Orcses.
乒半兽人
And they doesn't taste very nice, does they, precious?
那味道可不怎么样 对吧 宝贝
No.
对
Not very nice at all, my love.
简直糟透了 伙计
She hungers for sweeter meats.
她对人肉可是锋省欲滴
Hobbit meat.
昨比特人内
And when she throws away the bones and the empty clothes...
等把替比特人的骨头和衣服扔出来
.. then we will find it.
我们就能找到宝贝
And take it for me!
它就归我了
For us.
归我们
Yes. We meant "for us."
对 我是说“我们”
Gollum. Gollum.
咕噜 咕噜
The precious will be ours...
只要昨比特人一完蛋
...once the Hobbitses are dead!
宝贝就是我们的了
You treacherous little toad!
你这个阴险的小…
No! No! Master!
不 主人
No, Sam! Leave him alone!
不 山姆 放开他
I heard it from his own mouth. He means to murder us.
我听他亲口说的 他要谋害我们
Never! Sméagol wouldn't hurt a fly.
不会 斯米格连苍量都不伤害
He's a horrid, fat Hobbit...
这可怕的起比特胖猪
..who hates Sméagol...
仇视斯米格
...and who makes up nasty lies.
他血口喷人
You miserable little maggot! I'll stove your head in!
你这自吉的家伙 看我不征扁你
Sam!
山姆
Call me a liar? You're a liar!
你说我是骗子? 你这驴子
-You scare him off, we're lost! -! don't care! 1 can't do it, Mr. Frodo.
=- 你要是吓跑他 我们就完了 -我不管 我受够了 佛罗多老爷
-! won't wait around for him to kill us! -I'm not sending him away.
-我不能等着他来杀我们 -我不会让他走的
You don't see it, do you?
你还不明扎吗?
He's a villain.
他是恶棍
We can't do this by ourselves, Sam. Not without a guide.
光靠我们不行 山姆 我们需要问导
l need you on my side.
你得支持我
I'm on your side, Mr. Frodo.
我支持你 佛罗多老他
I know, Sam. I know.
我知道 山姆 我知道
Trust me.
相信我好了
Come, Sméagol.
过来 斯米格
The stars are veiled.
黑云遮月
Something stirs in the east.
东方正躁动不安
A sleepless malice.
杀机四估
The Eye of the enemy is moving.
敌人正栖尺欲动
What are you doing?
你在干什么
Pippin!
皮平
-What, are you mad? -I just want to look at it.
一你疯了吗 一我就是想看看
Just one more time.
就看一上腿
Put it back.
放回去
Pippin.
皮平
No!
不
He is here.
是索伦
see you.
我看到你了
Pippin!
皮平
Help! Gandalf, help!
救命 甘道夫
Someone help him!
快来救救他
Pippin!
皮平
Fool of a Took!
皮平你这傻瓜
Look at me.
看着我
Gandalf, forgive me.
甘道夫 原谅我
What did you see?
你看到什么了
A tree.
一棵树
There was a white tree...
一棵自色的树
...in a courtyard of stone.
在一个石头庭院里
It was dead.
已经枯死
The city was burning.
城市在燃烧
Minas Tirith? Is that what you saw?
是米那斯提力斯 就看到这些吗
I saw...
我看到
l saw him.
我看到他了
could hear his voice in my head.
他在我大脑里说话
And what did you tell him?
你们都说了什么
Speak!
快讲
He asked me my name. I didn't answer.
他问我名字 我没有回答
He hurt me.
他打了我
What did you tell him about Frodo and the Ring?
你告诉他佛罗多和魔戒的事了?
There was no lie in Pippin's eyes.
皮平的眼神证明他没有投谎
A fool...
一个傻瓜
...but an honest fool he remains.
尽管傻但还算诚实
He told Sauron nothing of Frodo and the Ring.
他没有向索伦泄露 有关佛罗多和魔戒的事
We've been strangely fortunate.
我们简直太幸运了
Pippin saw in the palantir a glimpse of the enemy's plan.
皮平竟然在魔球里看到敌人的阴谋
Sauron moves to strike the city of Minas Tirith.
索伦正要发兵进犯米那斯提力斯
His defeat at Helm's Deep showed our enemy one thing.
炙尔穆斯的失败让他明白一件事
He knows the heir of Elendil has come forth.
伊兰迪尔的后代已经重新崛起
Men are not as weak as he supposed.
人类并非他想象的那般脆弱
There is courage still, strength enough perhaps to challenge him.
他们有足够的力量向他挑战
Sauron fears this.
索伦最怕这一点
He will not risk the peoples of Middle-earth uniting under one banner.
他绝不会眼看着 中土世界的人民团结起来
He will raze Minas Tirith to the ground...
他要将米那斯提力斯夷为平地
...before he sees a king return to the throne of Men.
以免看到人类的国王重新合上王位
If the beacons of Gondor are lit, Rohan must be ready for war.
如果刚铎点燃烽火 罗罕国必须随时增援
Tell me...
先告诉我
... why should we ride to the aid of those who did not come to ours?
我们为什么要增援 那些对我们见死不救的人?
What do we owe Gondor?
我们欠刚色什么
-! will go. -No!
一我要去 -不
-They must be warned. -They will be.
-必须向他们报信 一是要报信
You must come to Minas Tirith by another road.
但你必须换一条路去米那斯提力斯
Follow the river and look to the black ships.
走水路 当心黑色帆船
Understand this:
大家要了明白
Things are now in motion that cannot be undone.
现在发生的一切已经不可逆转
[ ride for Minas Tirith...
我得骑马去米那斯提力斯
..and ] won't be going alone.
但不是一个人去
Of all the inquisitive Hobbits, Peregrin Took, you are the worst.
蚌比特人好奇心都很重 皮平 你是最过分的一个
Hurry! Hurry!
快点 快点
Where are we going?
我们这是去哪儿
Why did you look?
你为什么看魔球
Why do you always have to look?
你怎么什么都想探个究竟
-I don't know. I can't help it. -You never can.
-不知道 我忍不住 一你总是这样
I'm sorry, all right?
对不起 行了吧
-! won't do it again. -Don't you understand?
一我再也不看了 一你难道不知道吗
The enemy thinks you have the Ring.
索伦认为魔戒在你身上
He's going to be looking for you, Pip. They have to get you out of here.
他会到处找你 皮平 他们肯定会来这儿抓你
And you--? You're coming with me?
你和我一起走?
Merry?
梅里?
Come on.
快去吧
How far is Minas Tirith?
米那斯提力斯有多远?
Three days' ride, as the NazgAl flies.
以戒灵的速度 骑着马要跑三天
And you better hope we don't have one of those on our tail.
但愿他们不会跟在我们后面
Here.
给
Something for the road.
拿着路上用
The last of the Longbottom Leaf.
这是最后一包烟叶
I Know you've run out. You smoke too much, Pippin.
你的早用光了 你抽烟太多 皮和平
But-- But we'll see each other soon.
我们很快就会再见的
-Won't we? -I don't know.
一不是吗? 一不知道
I don't know what's going to happen.
我不知道会发生什么事
-Merry. -Run, Shadowfax.
一梅里 一影疾 跑起来吧
Show us the meaning of haste.
让我们知道什么叫速度
Merry!
梅里
Take her by the safest road.
带她走最安全的路
A ship lies anchored in the Grey Havens.
有一条船停靠在灰港
it waits to carry her across the sea.
等着带她横渡大海
The last journey of Arwen Undémiel.
这是亚孜' 安多米尔的最后之旅
There is nothing for you here...
这里无可留恋
..only death.
只有死亡
Lady Arwen...
亚孜公主
...we cannot delay.
我们不可耽搁
My lady!
公主
-Tell me what you have seen. -Arwen.
-告诉我你看到什么了 - 亚玉
You have the gift of foresight.
你可以酒察未来
What did you see?
你看见什么了
I looked into your future, and I saw death.
我看到了你的未来和你的死亡
But there is also life.
可是还有新的生命
You saw there was a child. You saw my son.
你看到一个小孩 看到了我的儿子
That future is almost gone.
那种可能微乎其微
But it is not lost.
但并韭没有希望
Nothing is certain.
希望不等于现实
Some things are certain.
有些事是命中注定
If l leave him now...
如果我离开他
...[ will regret it forever.
必将抱恨终生
It is time.
是了时候了
From the ashes a fire shall be woken
有灰蚂就会有火焰
A light from the shadow shall spring
有黑暗就会有光明
Renewed Shall be blade that was broken
残破圣剑将重现昔日锋艺
The crownless again shail be king
营范大地将迎来一代明君
Re-forge the sword.
接上断剑吧 父亲
Your hands are cold.
你的手很凉
The life of the Eldar is leaving you.
你正在失去精灵的神力
This was my choice.
这是我的选择
...there is no ship now that can bear me hence.
任何人都无法再让我离开这里
We've just passed into the realm of Gondor.
我们已经进入刚色王国
Minas Tirith.
米那斯提力斯
City of kings.
帝王之都
Make way!
内开
It's the tree.
这就是这棵树
Gandalf. Gandalf.
甘道夫 甘道夫
Yes, the White Tree of Gondor.
对 刚色的白树
The tree of the king.
帝王之树
Lord Denethor, however, is not king.
可是迪耐瑟并韭国王
He is a steward only, a caretaker of the throne.
他只是摄政王 王权代理人
Now listen carefully. Lord Denethor is Boromir's father.
仔细听着 迪耐琴大人 是博罗米尔的父亲
To give him news of his beloved son's death would be most unwise.
说出他爱子牺牲的消息很不明智
And do not mention Frodo or the Ring.
也不要提起佛罗多或魔戒
And say nothing of Aragorn either.
更不要提阿拉贡
In fact, it's better if you don't speak at all, Peregrin Took.
说白了 你最好免开尊口
Hail Denethor, son of Ecthelion, lord and steward of Gondor.
向您致敬迪耐瑟 爱克西里昂之子 刚铎的摄政王
I come with tidings in this dark hour, and with counsel.
在这危难之际 我给您带来了消息和建议
Perhaps you come to explain this.
也许你要问我解释这个
Perhaps you come to tell me why my son is dead.
也许你想向我解释我儿子何以身亡
Boromir died to save us...
博罗米尔为救我们而死
...my kinsman and me.
救我和我的同伴
-He fell defending us from many foes. -Pippin.
-他用生命保护了我们 -皮平
..in payment of this debt.
就算是我们对您的报答
Get up.
起来
My lord, there will be a time to grieve for Boromir...
我们以后还有时间京悼博罗米尔
...but it is not now.
可现在不行
War is coming.
战争即将发生
The enemy is on your doorstep. As steward, you are charged...
敌人已经兵临城下
You still have friends. You are not alone in this fight.
你还有盟友 不会孤军奋战
Send word to Théoden of Rohan. Light the beacons.
给罗罕国的塞奥顿报信 点燃烽火
You think you are wise, Mithrandir.
你自以为很高明 米斯兰达
Yet for all your subtleties, you have not wisdom.
尽管你很聪明 但你缺乏智慧
Do you think the eyes of the White Tower are blind?
你以为我们白塔人是睁眼瞎吗
l have seen more than you know.
我完全清楚你的伎俩
With your left hand you would use me as a shield against Mordor.
你用左手拿我作挡箭牌对抗魔多
And with your right you'd seek to supplant me.
再用你的右手把我除掉
know who rides with Théoden of Rohan.
我知道是谁跟罗罕国的塞奥顿串通
Oh, yes. Word has reached my ears of this Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
是的 阿拉贡我也早已有所耳闻 他是阿拉松之子
And I tell you now, I will not bow to this Ranger from the North...
你听着 我绝不会向北方游侠俯首称臣
...last of a ragged house long bereft of lordship.
他只是没落王族的最后残余
Authority is not given to you to deny the return of the king, steward.
你没权力拒绝自己的国王重返王位
The rule of Gondor is mine and no other's.
我是刚铎的统治者 不是别人
Come.
走吧
So I imagine this is just a ceremonial position.
我想这只是一个名誉头衔
I mean, they don't actually expect me to do any fighting.
我是说他们并不真的指望我去打仪
-Do they? -You're in the service of the steward now.
- 对吗 =-你现在是摄政王的侍从
You're going to have to do as you're told, Peregrin Took, guard of the Citadel.
你必须按命令行事 佩里格林 图克 城堡卫士
It's so quiet.
太安静了
It's the deep breath before the plunge.
这是大战之前的安静
I don't want to be in a battle...
我不想打仗
...but waiting on the edge of one I can't escape is even worse.
可想到必须打仗更让人感到不舒服
Is there any hope, Gandalf, for Frodo and Sam?
甘道夫 佛罗多和山姆 有成功的希望吗
There never was much hope.
从来就没有希望
Just a fool's hope.
那是傻瓜的希望
Our enemy is ready.
敌人已经准备就绪
His full strength's gathered.
索伦已经重兵在握
Not only Orcs, but Men as well.
除了半兽人 还有人类
Legions of Haradrim from the south...
来自南方的哈拉德林人部队
... mercenaries from the coast.
还有来自海岸的佣兵
All will answer Mordor's call.
他们都汇集到魔多的魔下
Come on.
来吧
This will be the end of Gondor as we know it.
看来刚铎王国凶多吉少
Here the hammer stroke will fall hardest.
这里势必会有一场恶战
If the river is taken, if the garrison at Osgiliath falls...
如果安都因河落入政手 如果奥斯吉力亚斯耕堡失陷
...the last defense of this city will be gone.
这座城市将失去所有屏障
But we have the White Wizard. That's got to count for something.
我们有握袍巫师 你不会坐视不管
Gandalf?
甘道夫?
Sauron has yet to reveal his deadliest servant...
索伦一定会派出他最得力的干将
...the one who will lead Mordor's armies in war.
由他统领魔多军队作战
The one they say no living man can Kill.
他们说没人能杀了他
The Witch-king of Angmar.
他是安格马的巫师
You've met him before.
你曾经见过他
He stabbed Frodo on Weathertop.
他在风云顶刺伤了佛罗多
He is the lord of the Nazgfl...
他是九大戒灵之首
...the greatest of the Nine.
是最大的戒灵
Minas Morgul is his fair.
米那斯魔窟是他的老洁
The Dead City.
死城
Very nasty place. Full of enemies.
最那恶的地方 到处都是敌人
Quick. Quick.
快点 快点
They will see. They will see.
他们会看到
Come away. Come away. Look, we have found it.
别走那儿 瞧 我们找到了
The way into Mordor.
这就是通往魔多的路
The secret stair.
秘密天梯
Climb.
有疏上去
-No, Mr. Frodo! -Not that way!
-不佛罗多老爷 一不是那边
-What's it doing? -No.
一他要干什么 -不
-They're calling me.
-他们在叫我
I can feel his blade.
我能感觉到他的利刃
We come to it at last.
天键时刻到了
The great battle of our time.
这将是一场世纪大战
Come away, Hobbits. We climb. We must climb.
来呀 起比特人 我们得私上去
The board is set.
棋盘摆好
The pieces are moving.
棋子都已就位
Peregrin Took, my lad, there is a task now to be done.
皮平 好孩子 给你个任务
Another opportunity for one of the Shire-folk to prove their great worth.
这是展示需比特人能力的好机会
You must not fail me.
不要让我失望
Quiet.
安静
-To the river. Quick. Quick. -Go. Go.
-去河边 快走 一快点
Come on.
来吧
Faster.
划快一点
Draw swords.
披剑
Hold! Hold!
挡住他们
What?
怎么会
Amon Din.
阿芝丁
The beacon. The beacon of Amon Din is lit.
烽火 阿蒙丁点燃了烽火
Hope is kindled.
也点燃了和希望
The beacons of Minas Tirith! The beacons are lit!
米那斯提力斯烽火 烽火点燃了
Gondor calls for aid.
刚铎请求救援
And Rohan will answer.
罗罕国马上出兵
Muster the Rohirrim.
命令军队集合
Assemble the army at Dunharrow.
军队在登哈洛待命
As many men as can be found. You have two days.
人越多越好 给你两天时间
On the third, we ride for Gondor and war.
第三天开赴刚色作战
-Forward. -Very good, sir.
一前进 -很好
-Gamling. -My lord.
-加姆林 -陛下
Make haste across the Riddermark.
全速跨越罗罕平原
Summon every able-bodied man to Dunharrow.
召集所有身强力壮者到登哈洛
I will.
遵命
-Will you ride with us? -Just to the encampment.
一你也一起去吗 -我只到营地
It's tradition for the women of the court to farewell the men.
按规矩王室妇女要送男人一程
The men have found their captain.
士兵们终于有了领导者
They will follow you into battle, even to death.
他们将跟随你走向战场 万死不辞
You have given us hope.
你就是希望
So it is before the walis of Minas Tirith...
米那斯提力斯城墙最终将决定
...the doom of our time will be decided.
我们这个时代最后的命运
Now is the hour. Riders of Rohan, oaths you have taken.
接受考验吧 罗罕国的骑士 你们曾经立下誓言
Now, fulfill them all. To lord and land!
现在到了兑现的时候 为了国王和祖国
Faramir!
法拉米尔
We can't hold them. The city is lost.
我们项不住了 城池已经失守
Tell the men to break cover. We ride for Minas Tirith.
命令大家撤退 返回米那斯提力斯
Take cover!
快找掩护
Fall back. Fall back to Minas Tirith!
撤出阵地 撤退到米那斯提力斯
Fall back!
快撤退
-Retreat! Retreat! -Come on!
-撤退 撤退 一快点
The age of Men is over.
人类终于完重了
The time of the Orc has come.
半兽人的时代已经开始
Take cover!
快找掩护
Take cover, my lord!
大人 快找掩护
It's coming!
他们来了
-It's Mithrandir. -The White Rider!
-是米斯兰达 -外袍骑士
Pull!
打开城门
Mithrandir.
米斯兰达
They broke through our defenses.
他们冲破了我们的防线
They've taken the bridge and the west bank.
占领了大桥还有西河岸
-Battalions of Orcs are crossing the river. -It is as the Lord Denethor predicted.
一半兽人大军正在过河 - 不出迪耐瑟摄政王预料
-Long has he foreseen this doom. -Foreseen and done nothing.
-他早就知道会这样 - 早就知道那为何不为
Faramir?
法拉米尔?
This is not the first Halfling to have crossed your path.
你并非第一次见到起比特人
No.
对
You've seen Frodo and Sam?
你见到佛罗多和山姆?
-Where? When? -In Ithilien.
-在哪儿 什么时候 一在伊西力安
Not two days ago.
大概两天前
Gandalf, they're taking the road to the Morgul Vale.
甘道夫 他们正去往魔审谷
And then the pass of Cirith Ungol.
然后会通过西力斯昂哥隘口
What does that mean?
很难走吗
-What's wrong? -Faramir, tell me everything.
一怎么了 一法拉米尔 快告诉我详情
Careful, master. Careful.
当心 主人 当心
Very far to fall.
下面深不见底
Very dangerous are the stairs.
这天梯非常危险
Come, master.
来呀 主人
Come to Sméagol.
到斯米格这儿来
Mr. Frodo.
佛罗多老他
Get back, you!
你滚开
Don't touch him!
不许碰他
Why does he hates poor Sméagol?
他为什么讨厌可怜的斯米格
What has Sméagol ever done to him?
斯米格怎么得罪他了
Master?
主人
Master carries heavy burden.
主人身负重任
Sméagol knows. Heavy, heavy burden.
斯米格知道 非常非常沉重
Fat one cannot know.
那胖子是无法理解的
Sméagol look after master.
让斯米格照顾主人
He wants it.
他想要那个
He needs it. Sméagol sees it in his eye.
他需要它 斯米格看他眼神就知道
Very soon he will ask you for it. You will see.
他早晚会开口讨要 等着瞧
The fat one will take it from you.
那胖子会抢走你的魔戒
Send forth all legions.
派出所有军队
Do not stop the attack until the city is taken.
不攻下那座城我拆不罢休
Slay them all.
把他们全都杀光
-What of the wizard? -I will break him.
-那个焉师呢 =我要让他威风扫地
What of Théoden's riders?
塞奥顿的骑兵呢
Will Rohan's army come?
罗罕军队会来吗
Mithrandir.
米斯兰达
Courage is the best defense that you have now.
勇气是你们最坚固的防线
Here do I swear fealty and service to Gondor...
我在此庄严宣兰效忠刚色
. ..1M peace or war...
无论和平战争
...in living or dying...
生离死别
..from....
从
From this hour henceforth...
从今往后
...until my lord release me...
除韭主人宣布终止
...or death take me.
或者死神降临
And I shall not forget it...
我将铭记你的寿言
...nor fail to reward that which is given.
也一定赐给你应得的奖赏
Fealty with love.
忠诚得恩宠
Valor with honor.
勇敢得荣誉
Disloyalty with vengeance.
背信弃义也必得惩治
1 do not think we should so lightly abandon the outer defenses...
我们不该如此轻易放弃外城防御
... defenses that your brother long held intact.
你哥哥在世时固守了多年
-What would you have me do? -I will not yield...
-那你要我怎么样? 一我不想失去
...the river in Pelennor unfought.
帕兰诺平原和胡堡
Osgiliath must be retaken.
奥斯吉力亚斯必须夺回
My lord, Osgiliath is overrun.
父王 奥斯吉力亚斯已经失陷
Much must be risked in war.
战争本身就必须冒险
Is there a captain here who still has the courage to do his lord's will?
难道没有一个人 勇于遵照君王的意愿行事吗
You wish now that our places had been exchanged...
你一定很想调换我们的位置
...that I had died and Boromir had lived.
让我去死而让博罗米尔活着
Yes.
是的
I wish that.
我希望那样
Since you were robbed of Boromir...
既然你已失去了他
...[ will do what 1 can in his stead.
我愿代他完成使命
If 1 should return, think better of me, Father.
如果我能生还 请改变对我的看法
That will depend on the manner of your return.
那我还要看你如何生还
What are you up to?
你干什么?
Sneaking off, are we?
想溜是不是?
Sneaking?
想汶?
Fat Hobbit is always so polite.
霍比特胖子真懂礼歼
Sméagol shows them secret ways that nobody else could find...
斯米格为他们带路 这条路只有我知道
..and they say "sneak."
他们还说我“想溜”
Sneak?
想汶?
Very nice friend. Oh, yes, my precious.
真是好朋友 是的 亲爱的够意思
-Very nice, very nice. -All right. All right!
- 真是好极了 - 行咬 行图
You just startled me is all.
我就是吓了一跳 没别的
What were you doing?
那你想干什么
Sneaking.
想溜呀
Fine. Have it your own way.
好 随你的便吧
I'm sorry to wake you, Mr. Frodo.
对不起叫醒你 佛罗多老公
We have to be moving on.
我们该动身了
It's dark still.
天还黑着呢
It's always dark here.
这儿总是黑的
It's gone!
没有了
-The Elven bread. -What?
一精灵代干 一什么?
That's all we have left.
那是我们仅有的口粮
He took it. He must have!
是他拿了 一定是他
Sméagol? No, no, not poor Sméagol.
斯米格? 不是可怜的斯米格
Sméagol hates nasty Elf bread.
斯米格讨厌精灵傍干
You're a lying wretch! What did you do with it?!
你这可恶的骗子 拿去干什么了
He doesn't eat it.
他不吃那个
-He can't have taken it. -Look.
-不会是他拿了 - 瞧
What's this?
这是什么
Crumbs on his jacketses. He took it!
他衣服上有人饼干屑 是他拿的
He took it.
是他拿的
l seen him. He's always stuffing his face when master's not looking.
我看见过 主人一不注意他就往嘴里塞东西
That's a filthy lie!
你血口喷人
You stinking, two-faced sneak!
你这两面三刀的家人
-Sam! -Call me--
-山姆 -你敢说是我
Stop it!
住手
Sam!
山姆
-l'IL kill him! -Sam! No!
-我要打死他 -山姆 不
Oh, my-- I'm sorry. didn't mean it to go so far. 1 was just so-- So angry.
对不起 我没想这样做 我只不过太生气了
Here, just-- Let's just rest a bit.
来吧 咱们歇一会儿
-'m all right. -No.
-我没事 -不
No, you're not all right. You're exhausted.
你有事 你累坏了
It's that Gollum.
都怪咕噜
It's this place.
怪这个破地方
It's that thing around your neck.
还有你脖子上那个东西
I could help a bit.
我可以替你分担
I could carry it for a while.
帮你戴一会儿
Carry it for a while.
我可以帮你
I could carry it...1 could carry it.
没关系
Share the load...Share the load... the load...the load.
交给我好了
Get away!
走开
I don't want to keep it.
我并不想要它
I just want to help.
只想帮忙你
See? See?
瞧瞧? 瞧瞧?
He wants it for himself.
他想占有它
Shut up, you!
你住口
Go away! Get out of here!
走开 一边去
No, Sam.
不 山姆
It's you.
你得走
I'm sorry, Sam.
很抱歉 山姆
But he's a liar.
他是个骗子
He's poisoned you against me.
他在挑拨我们俩
You can't help me anymore.
你帮不了我了
You don't mean that.
这不是真心话
Go home.
回家吧
Faramir!
法拉米尔
Your father's will has turned to madness.
你父亲的想法不可理喻
Do not throw away your life so rashly.
你不能这样草率地就送命
Where does my allegiance lie if not here?
我不为刚铎效命还能为谁
Your father loves you, Faramir.
你父亲是爱你的 法拉米尔
He will remember it before the end.
他早晚会明白这一点
Can you sing, Master Hobbit?
会唱歌吗 震比特人?
Well...
会吧
yes.
至少
At least, well enough for my own people.
能给家乡的人唱几名
But we have no songs for great halls...
可我的歌不适合在王宫演唱
...and evil times.
尤其在倒霉时
And why should your songs be unfit for my halls?
为什么不适合在王宫演唱
Come, sing me a song.
来 唱一首吧
Make way for the king.
给陛下让路
Make way.
让开
The king is here.
国王来了
My lord.
陛下
Hail to you, sire.
国王万岁 万岁
Grimbold, how many?
葛林伯 你有多少人
I bring 500 men from the Westfold, my lord.
500多西谷人 陛下
We have 300 more from Fenmarch, Théoden King.
还有300多人来自沼境 塞奥顿国王
-Where are the riders from Snowbourn? -None have come, my lord.
-雪界河骑士在哪儿 一他们还没来 陛下
Six thousand spears.
6千名长矛手
Less than half of what I'd hoped for.
不到我希望的一半
Six thousand will not be enough to break the lines of Mordor.
6于长矛不足以攻破魔多的防线
More will come.
还会来的
Every hour lost hastens Gondor's defeat.
拖延只能加速刚色的失败
We have till dawn, then we must ride.
找晓前我们必须出发
The horses are restless...
马匹躁动不安
...and the men are quiet.
士兵们却很安静
They grow nervous in the shadow of the mountain.
山区的阴暗使他们感到紧张
That road there...
那儿有条路
... where does that lead?
通向哪里
It is the road to the Dimholt, the door under the mountain.
通身丁祸 黑暗之门
None who venture there ever return.
没人能从那里回来
That mountain is evil.
那是亡灵之山
Aragorn.
阿拉贡
Let's find some food.
咱们弄点吃的吧
There.
好了
A true esquire of Rohan.
一名真正的罗罕骑士
I'm ready.
准备完毕
Sorry.
对不起
It isn't all that dangerous.
它没什么可怕的
It's not even sharp.
一点也不锋利
Well, that's no good. You won't kill many Orcs with a blunt blade.
那怎么行 钝剑杀不了几个半兽人
Come on.
跟我来
To the smithy. Go!
去找铁匠 走吧
You should not encourage him.
你不应该喜动他
You should not doubt him.
你不应该怀疑他
1 do not doubt his heart, only the reach of his arm.
我并不怀疑他的心 只是他的用膊太短
Why should Merry be left behind?
为什么要让梅里留下
He has as much cause to go to war as you.
他和你一样有理由上战场
Why can he not fight for those he loves?
他为什么不能为所爱的人战斗
{ choose a mortal life.
我选择了凡人的生活
l wish I could've seen him...
我希望能见他
...one last time.
最后一面
Sir?
先生?
King Théoden awaits you, my lord.
塞奥顿国王想苑您
I take my leave.
我先出去了
My lord Elrond.
埃尔伦
I come on behalf of one whom I love.
我代表我所爱的人而来
Arwen is dying.
亚玉快不行了
She will not long survive the evil that now spreads from Mordor.
魔多的政恶笼直大地
The light of the Evenstar is failing.
亚孜已等不到它的消失 夜明星即将陨落
As Sauron's power grows, her strength wanes.
索伦的魔力越强 亚玫的力量越弱
Arwen's life is now tied to the fate of the Ring.
魔戒的命运决定着亚玉的生死
The Shadow is upon us, Aragorn.
马云笼罩着我们 阿拉贡
The end has come.
末日到了
It will not be our end, but his.
不是我们的 是索伦的
You ride to war, but not to victory.
你走向战场 不是走向胜利
Sauron's armies march on Minas Tirith, this you know.
索伦的军队正在攻打米那斯提力斯
But in secret he sends another force which will attack from the river.
他还在暗中派军队 从河对面发起攻击
A fleet of Corsairs ships sails from the south.
一只昂巴海盗船正从南方驶来
They'll be in the city in two days.
两天后就将抵达城下
You're outnumbered, Aragorn.
你们袁不政众
You need more men.
必须派兵增援
There are none.
无兵可派
There are those who dwell in the mountain.
亡灵之山还游污着很多死魂灵
Murderers...
他们是凶手
... traitors.
和背叛者
You would call upon them to fight?
你想让他们出来作战吗
They believe in nothing.
他们没有信仰
They answer to no one.
不听任何人召唤
They will answer to the king of Gondor.
他们会听从刚铎国王的指令
Anduril, the Flame of the West, forged from the shards of Narsil.
安都瑞尔由西方之炎 和纳希尔断剑重铸而成
Sauron will not have forgotten the Sword of Elendil.
索伦永远不会忘记伊兰迪尔圣剑
The blade that was broken shall return to Minas Tirith.
曾经破碎的剑须重返米那斯提力斯
The man who can wield the power of this sword...
有力量挥舞这把圣剑的人
...can summon to him an army more deadly than any that walks this earth.
可以召集千军万马 所向披摩
Put aside the Ranger.
你不再是健步侠
Become who you were born to be.
你应该成为国王
Take the Dimholt road.
走上亡者之道
Why are you doing this?
你为什么离开?
The war lies to the east. You cannot leave on the eve of battle.
战斗将在东方打响 大战前夕
You cannot abandon the men.
别殷下你的士兵
. Eowyn....
伊欧玫
We need you here.
我们需要你留下
Why have you come?
你为什么要来?
Do you not know?
你真不知道?
It is but a shadow and a thought that you love.
你的爱是虚幻和不真实的
I cannot give you what you seek.
我不能接受你这份爱
Just where do you think you're off to?
你到底想去哪儿?
Not this time.
这次不行
This time you must stay, Gimli.
这次你必须留下 金需
Have you learned nothing of the stubbornness of Dwarves?
难道你没有领教过矮人的固执吗
You might as well accept it. We're going with you, laddie.
你最好还是顺着我 我们要跟随你
-What's happening? -Where is he going?
-出了什么事 一他要去哪儿
Where's he going?
他要去哪儿
I don't understand.
真搞不懂
Lord Aragorn!
阿拉贡大人
Why does he leave on the eve of battle?
他为什么在大战前离开?
He leaves because there is no hope.
他离开是因为失去了希望
He leaves because he must.
他离开是因为必须离开
Too few have come.
来的人太少了
We cannot defeat the armies of Mordor.
我们无法打败魔多的军队
No...
对
...we cannot.
打不败
But we will meet them in battle nonetheless.
但我们还是要跟他们决一死战
I have left instruction.
我已写下诏书
The people are to follow your rule in my stead.
你将取代我向民众发号施邻
Take up my seat in the Golden Hall.
登上金殿的宝座 保卫罗罕王国
Long may you defend Edoras...
万一我战场失利
...if the battle goes ill.
你要全力捍卫伊多拉斯
What other duty would you have me do, my lord?
还有什么任务需要我完成
Duty?
任务?
No.
没有
I would have you smile again...
我只想看到你的笑容
...not grieve for those whose time has come.
不要为行将就木的人悲伤
You shall live to see these days renewed...
你们一定会再过上和平生活
...and no more despair.
不要失去信心
What kind of army would linger in such a place?
什么军队会驻在这种地方?
One that is cursed.
受到诅咒的军队
Long ago, the Men of the Mountains swore an oath...
很久以前亡灵之山的人曾经发过誓
...to the last king of Gondor...
向刚铎末代国王保证
...to come to his aid...
帮助他打败
...to fight.
政人
But when the time came...
可是有一天
... when Gondor's need was dire...
当刚色急需援助时
... they fled...
他们却逃走了
.. vanishing into the darkness of the mountain.
消失在亡灵之山深处
And so Isildur cursed them...
于是埃西铎国王诅咒他们
...never to rest until they had fulfilled their pledge.
在他们履行诺言前永远不得安宁
The very warmth of my blood seems stole away.
我怎么觉得浑身冰凉
The way is shut.
黑暗之门
It was made by those who are dead.
它由那些死魂灵建造
And the Dead keep it.
并且由他们把守
The way is shut.
大门紧闭
Brego!
布理哥
1 do not fear death.
死亡并不可怕
Well, this is a thing unheard-of.
简直骇人听闻
An Elf will go underground where a Dwarf dare not?
精灵人去了地下而矮人反倒不敢
Oh.
真是的
Oh, I'd never hear the end of it.
我可不想被人当成笑柄
We must ride light and swift.
我们必须轻装前进马不停蹄
It is a long road ahead.
路还很长
And man and beast must reach the end with the strength to fight.
人马必须保持足够体力投入战斗
Little Hobbits do not belong in war, Master Meriadoc.
昨比特人不适合打仗 梅里先生
All my friends have gone to battle.
朋友们都上了战场
I would be ashamed to be left behind.
我留下会无地自容
It is a three-day gallop to Minas Tirith.
骑马去米那斯提力斯要三天
And none of my riders can bear you as a burden.
哪个骑士肯带上你这个包裕
I want to fight.
我要去战斗
I will say no more.
别再说了
Ride with me.
你跟着我
My lady.
公主
Form up! Move out!
列队 出发
Ride!
出发
Ride now to Gondor!
向刚铎前进
Who enters my domain?
是谁来到我的领地?
One who will have your allegiance.
一个要你履行诺言的人
The Dead do not suffer the living to pass.
死去的人不能容忍活人由此经过
You will suffer me.
可你得容忍我
The way is shut.
黑暗之门已关上
It was made by those who are dead.
它是由死魂灵建造
And the Dead keep it.
由死魂灵把守
The way is shut.
死亡之门紧闭
Now you must die.
你们必死无疑
I summon you to fulfill your oath.
我命令你必须履行诺言
None but the king of Gondor may command me.
只有刚铎国王有这个权力
That line was broken.
圣剑早已断裂
It has been remade.
它已重新铸就
Fight for us...
为我战斗
...and regain your honor.
挽回你们的名誉
What say you?
你们现在如何决定吧
You waste your time, Aragorn.
别溪费时间 阿拉贡
They had no honor in life, they have none now in death.
他们活着都不讲名淮 死了就更不用说了
Iam Isildur's heir.
我是埃西铎的后毅
Fight for me...
为我而战吧
...and I will hold your oaths fulfilled.
我将承认你们履行了诺言
What say you?
决定吧
Open the gate! Quick!
把门打开 快
Quick! Hurry!
快点
Faramir!
法拉米尔
Say not that he has fallen.
不要说他已经去了
They were outnumbered.
他们彭不政众
None survived.
全部阵亡
Fear.
恐惧
The city is rank with it.
城里充满恐惧
Let us ease their pain.
应该安奈他们
Release the prisoners.
把俘虏们放回去
Catapults!
放
My sons are spent.
我儿子死了
My line has ended.
我断了香火
He's alive!
他还活着
The House of Stewards has failed.
摄政王府就此骨省了
He needs medicine, my lord.
他需要和急救 大人
My line has ended!
我断了香火
My lord!
大人
Rohan...
罗罕人
...has deserted us.
苑死不救
Théoden's betrayed me.
塞奥顿背信痉义
Abandon your posts!
你们全都走
Flee! Flee for your lives!
快去逃命吧
Prepare for battle!
准备战斗
Hurry, men! To the wall! Defend the wall!
勇士们 回到城墙 保卫城墙
Over here!
这里
Return to your posts!
返回各自岗位
Send these foul beasts into the abyss.
把那些怪兽打入地狱
Stay where you are.
谁也不许动
We need more rubble!
我们需要更多石块
Watch out!
当心
Down to the lower level. Quick!
到下面一层 快
Double up, men!
快点
Hold them back! Do not give in to fear.
打退他们 不要害怕
Stand to your posts! Fight!
坚守岗位 放
Not to the towers!
打烂那些发射架
Aim for the trolls! Kill the trolls!
瞄准食人妖 消灭它们
Bring them down!
杀死它们
Fight them back!
打退他们
Peregrin Took!
佩里格林 图克
-Go back to the Citadel! -They'd called us out to fight.
一快回城堡去 一你叫我们出来的
This is no place for a Hobbit.
这地方不适合蝴比特人
Guard of the Citadel, indeed.
你是真正的城堡卫士
Now, back, up the hill. Quickly. Quick!
回到山上去 快去
Grond! Grond! Grond! Grond!
万龙德 葛龙德
In there.
进去
What is this place?
这是什么地方
Master must go inside the tunnel.
主人必须要进到酒里去
Now that I'm here, I don't think 1 want to.
走到这儿 我再也不想往里走了
It's the only way.
这是必经之路
Go in...
进去
...0F go back.
要么就回家
I can't go back.
我不能回去
-What's that smell? -Orcses' filth.
一这是什么味儿 一半兽人的臭味
Orcses come in here sometimes.
他们有了时来这上儿
Hurry.
快点
Sméagol?
斯米格?
Over here.
我在这儿
It's sticky. What is it?
粘糊糊的 这是什么东西
You'll see.
你会知道
Oh, yes.
是的
Sméagol?
斯米格?
Sam.
山姆
And you, Frodo Baggins...
佛罗多“' 巴金斯
...4 give you the light of Earendil, our most beloved star.
我把埃兰迪尔之光送给你 它是我们心爱的明星
May it be a light for you in dark places...
当你圣入无边的黑暗时
...when all other lights go out.
愿它能带给你光明
Naughty little fly
淘气小飞虫
Why does he cry?
喻喻叫不停
Caught in a web
失足入罗网
Soon you'll be...
要成
Eaten.
腹中物
Got away, did it, precious?
你居然逃掉了 亲爱的?
Not this time.
这回休想
-Not this time! -No!
-这回休想 -不
It wasn't us. It wasn't us!
不是我 不是我
Sméagol wouldn't hurt master.
斯米格不会伤害主人
You must believe us.
你要相信我
It was the precious.
是宝贝的的鬼
The precious made us do it.
是宝贝驱使我干的
I have to destroy it, Sméagol.
我必须毁掉它 斯米格
have to destroy it for both our sakes.
为了你和我 必须毁掉它
No!
不
I'm so sorry, Sam.
对不起 山姆
I'm so sorry.
对不起
This task was appointed to you, Frodo of the Shire.
这是你的使命 夏尔国的便罗多
if you do not find a way...
如果你做不到
...10 one will.
没人能做到
Back to the gate!
守住城门去
Hurry!
快
No tomb for Denethor and Faramir.
迪耐琴和法拉米尔不要坟墓
No long, slow sleep of death embalmed.
我不想抹好香宫长眠地下
We shall burn, like the heathen kings of old.
我要像异教徒的国王苦于烈火
Bring wood and oil.
拿木柴和油来
Steady.
坚持住
You are soldiers of Gondor.
你们是刚铎勇士
No matter what comes through that gate, you will stand your ground.
无论什么进入那道大门 你们都不能后退半步
Volley!
弓箭
Fire!
放
Let him go, you filth.
放开他 臭东西
Let him go!
放开他
You will not touch him again.
不许你再碰他
Come on and finish it.
你冲我来吧
Back!
滚开 滚开
Mr. Frodo.
佛罗多老他
Oh, no.
不
Frodo.
佛罗多
Mr. Frodo.
佛罗多老他
Wake up.
你醒醒
Don't leave me here alone.
别把我丢下
Don't go where I can't follow.
别去我不能去的地方
Wake up.
醒醒
Not asleep.
你不是睡了
Dead.
你死了
What's this?
这是什么
Looks like old Shelob's been having a bit of fun.
看来老蜂几玩得很开心
Killed another one, has she?
又型死一个吧?
No.
不
This fellow ain't dead.
这个家伙还没死
Not dead?
还没死?
She jabs him with her stinger, and he goes as limp as a boned fish.
她用毒刺把他给麻醉了 让他失去知觉任其摆布
Then she has her way with them.
想怎么吃就怎么吃
That's how she likes to feed.
她就喜欢那种吃法
Fresh blood.
味道鲜得很
Get him to the tower!
把他和弄上塔楼
Samwise, you fool.
山姆 你个傻瓜
This scum will be awake in a couple of hours.
这家伙几个小时后就会醒来
Then he'll wish he'd never been born.
到那时他就生不如死了
The house of his spirit crumbles.
灵魂与肉体即将分离
He is burning.
他在发烧
Already burning.
他在燃烧
He's not dead.
正在燃烧
He's not dead!
他还没死 他还没死
No! No!
不
-Farewell, Peregrin, son of Paladin. -No! No! No!
一再见了 帕拉丁之子皮平 -不不
release you from my service.
我解除你的故约
Go now and die in what way seems best to you.
去找个最适合的方法结束生命吧
Pour oil on the wood!
往木此上泌油
Come on! Move your feet!
加把劲 快
-Hurry along there! Hurry along! -Gandalf!
一你们快点 一鞭道夫
Where is Gandalf?
甘道夫在哪儿
Gandalf!
甘道夫
Retreat!
撤退
The city is breached!
外城已被攻破
Fall back to the second level!
撤到环城防线
Get the women and children out!
带上妇女和孩子
Get them out!
全都带上
Retreat!
撤退
Come on. Come on.
快呀
Move into the city. Kill all in your path.
打进城去 斩尽杀绝
Take them down!
干掉他们
Fight. Fight to the last man!
战斗 战斗到底
Fight for your lives!
为生存而战
Courage, Merry.
勇敢些 梅里
Courage for our friends.
为了我们的朋友
Form ranks, you maggots. Form ranks!
站好 一群废物 站好
Pikes in front. Archers behind.
长矛手在前 弓箭手在后
Eomer, take your éored down the left flank.
伊欧墨 带着你的人马从左侧迁回
Flank ready.
准备出发
Gamling, follow the king's banner down the center.
加姆林 你跟随国王战旗走中路
Grimbold, take your company right after you pass the wall.
葛林伯 你的人进攻右路
Forth, and fear no darkness!
杀入城围 无所畏惧
Arise, arise, Riders of Théoden!
塞奥顿的骑士们
Spears shall be shaken, shields shall be splintered...
挥舞你们的长矛 戳穿政人的铠甲
...a sword-day, a red day...
杀政之日
...ere the sun rises!
血战到底 直至黎明
Whatever happens, stay with me. I'll look after you.
不管怎样都要跟着我 我会照顾你
Ride now!
杀咱
...and the world's ending!
杀
Forth Eorlingas!
罗罕人冲啊
Fire!
放
Death!
冲啊 杀
Fire at will!
发射
Gandalf!
甘道夫
Gandalf! Denethor has lost his mind!
甘道夫 迪耐瑟他疯了
He's burning Faramir alive!
他要烧死法拉米尔
Up! Quickly!
快 上马
Set a fire in our flesh.
在我们身下燃起烈火
Stay this madness!
不许明来
No!
不
You will not take my son from me!
你不能抢走我儿子
No! No!
不不
Faramir.
法拉米尔
So passes Denethor, son of Ecthelion.
爱克西里昂之子 迪耐瑟终于走了
Drive them to the river!
把他们赶下河去
Make safe the city!
把城堡夺回来
Re-form the line!
重新列队
Sound the charge! Take them head-on!
吹响号角 前进
Charge!
冲邮
Take the reins. Pull him left!
握紧强
Left!
向左融 向左
Aim for their heads!
瞄准头部
Bring it down! Bring it down! Bring it down!
杀死他们 杀死他们
Merry!
梅里
I didn't think it would end this way.
真没想到会这样结束
End?
结束?
No, the journey doesn't end here.
不 人生永远不会结束
Death is just another path...
死亡只是另外一种人生
...one that we all must take.
我们都必须经历
The grey rain curtain of this world rolls back...
这个世界的灰色雨幕终将卷起
...and all turns to silver glass.
大地将化为一片银白
And then you see it.
那时你将看到
What, Gandalf?
什么 甘道夫?
See what?
看到什么
White shores...
白色的海岸
..and beyond.
和远方
A far green country...
无边无际的绿野
...under a swift sunrise.
喷薄而出的朝阳
Well...
响
...that isn't so bad.
看来还不错
No.
对
No, it isn't.
是不错
Rally to me! To me!
都跟我来 跟我来
Feast on his flesh.
我把他吃掉
I will kill you if you touch him.
你敢碰他我就杀了你
Do not come between the NazgUl and his prey.
不要妨碍戒灵享用美餐
Late as usual, pirate scum!
总是姗姗来迟 臭海盗
There's knife-work here needs doing.
一场肉搏战正等着你们
Come on, you sea rats! Get off your ships!
快点 该死的海老鼠 快下船
There's plenty for the both of us.
这回可以大开杀戒了
May the best Dwarf win.
看你能不能赢过我们矮人
You fool.
傻瓜
No man can kill me.
男人奈何不了我
Die now.
去死吧
lam no man.
我不是男人
-Fifteen! Sixteen! -Seventeen!
-十五 十六 -十七
-Twenty-nine! -Legolas!
一二十九 一著戈拉斯
Thirty-three, thirty-four.
三十三 三十四
That still only counts as one!
那只能算一个
All right, then. Come on!
好 来吧
I know your face...
我认出了你的脸庞
. ... Eowyn.
伊欧玫
My eyes darken.
我不行了
No.
不
lam going to save you.
我会救你
You already did.
你已经救了我
. Eowyn...
伊欧玫
...my body is broken.
我的身体已经破碎
You have to let me go.
你就让我走吧
go to my fathers...
我去找我的父辈
...in whose mighty company...
他们英名长存
...[ shall not now feel ashamed.
我没有给他们丢脸
. Eowyn.
伊欧玫
Release us.
放了我们吧
Bad idea.
那可不行
Very handy in a tight spot, these lads, despite the fact they're dead.
这些家伙插管用 尽管他们是魂灵
You gave us your word.
你曾经答应过
I hold your oath fulfilled.
我承认你们履行了诺言
Go.
走吧
Be at peace.
愿你们安宁
Merry.
梅里
Merry, it's me.
梅里 是我
It's Pippin.
是皮平
I knew you'd find me.
我就知道你会找我
Yes.
是的
Are you going to leave me?
我不行了是吗
No, Merry.
不 梅里
I'm going to look after you.
我会照顾你
Hands off!
放下
That shiny shirt, that's mine.
那件内光衣是我的
It's going to the Great Eye, along with everything else.
我要献给索伦王 包括这儿的一切
I don't take orders from stinking Morgul rats!
我可不听魔窟鼠辈的命令
You touch it, and I'll stick this blade in your gut.
你要础它 我就把刀插进你肚子
The scum tried to knife me.
这个家伙想杀我
Kill him!
宰了他
That's for Frodo!
为了佛罗多
And for the Shire!
这是为了夏尔国
And that's for my old Gaffer!
这个为了我老区
Stop your squealing, you dunghill rat.
别叫了 你这该死的小东西
I'm gonna bleed you like a stuck pig.
我要像杀猪一样给你放放血
Not if! stick you first.
我先放你的血
Sam!
山姆
Oh, Sam, I'm so sorry.
山姆 对不起
Sorry for everything.
真的很对不起
-Let's get you out of here. -It's too late. It's over.
=我们赶快离开这里 一来不及了 太晚了
They've taken it. Sam...
让他们抢走了 山姆
...they took the Ring.
他们抢走了魔戒
Begging your pardon, but they haven't.
对不起 他们没抢走
I thought I'd lost you.
我还以为你死了
So I took it.
于是我就拿了它
Only for safekeeping.
只是为了保住它
Give it to me.
把它给我
Give me the Ring, Sam.
把魔戒给我
Sam.
山姆
Give me the Ring.
给我魔戒
You must understand.
你必须明握
The Ring is my burden.
魔戒太沉重了
It will destroy you, Sam.
他能毁掉你 山姆
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
走吧 佛罗多老爷
We best find you some clothes.
我最好给你拷些衣服
You can't go walking through Mordor in naught but your skin.
你总不能光着膀子到魔多去
We did it, Mr. Frodo.
成功了 佛罗多老爷
We made it to Mordor.
我们终于到了魔多
There are so many of them.
敌人可真多啊
We'll never get through unseen.
这样进去迟早被发现
It's him, the Eye.
是他 那只魔眼
We have to go in there, Mr. Frodo.
我们必须去那儿 佛罗多老他
There's nothing for it.
别无选择
Come on. Let's just make it down the hill for starters.
来吧 咱们就把这里作为起点
Frodo has passed beyond my sight.
佛罗多已经走出我的视野
If Sauron had the Ring, we would know it.
如果索伦拿到魔戒我们就会知道
It's only a matter of time.
那只是时间问题
He has suffered a defeat, yes...
虽然他吃了败侈
...but behind the walls of Mordor, . . our enemy is regrouping.
但正在魔多高墙背后重新集结军队
Let him stay there.
让他死在那儿吧
Let him rot! Why should we care?
一天天腐烂 我们才不操心呢
Because 10,000 Orcs now stand between Frodo and Mount Doom.
因为在佛罗多和末日山之间 还有一万半兽人大军
I've sent him to his death.
是我让他们走上了不归路
No.
不
There is still hope for Frodo.
佛罗多还有希望
He needs time and safe passage across the plains of Gorgoroth.
他需要时间和安全通道 穿过葛哥洛斯平原
-We can give him that. -How?
=我们能帮他办到 一怎么帮
Draw out Sauron's armies.
把索伦的军队引出来
Empty his lands.
让魔多成为空城
Then we gather our full strength and march on the Black Gate.
然后我们就集中兵力攻击黑暗之门
We cannot achieve victory through strength of arms.
以我们的兵力很难战胜索伦
Not for ourselves.
不是为了取胜
But we can give Frodo his chance if we keep Sauron's Eye fixed upon us.
只要我们能够吸引索伦的注意力
Keep him blind to all else that moves.
就能给佛罗多创造机会 让索伦无暇顾及其它事情
A diversion.
瞒天过海
Sauron will suspect a trap.
索伦会怀疑有诠
He will not take the bait.
他不会轻易上钧
Certainty of death...
肯定会有伤亡
... small chance of success...
成功的可能性很小
... what are we waiting for?
那还等什么
To the Gate, you slugs!
去大门那儿 答蛋
Move it! To the Gate!
快点 到大门去
Look, the Orcs...
瞧 半兽人
..they're moving off.
他们离开了
You see, Mr. Frodo...
你看 佛罗多老他
...some luck at last.
我们开始走运了
Take mine.
喝我的吧
There's a few drops left.
还剩了一点
There will be none left for the return journey.
回去时就没得喝了
I don't think there will be a return journey, Mr. Frodo.
我觉得回去的可能性不大 佛罗多
Frodo, get down!
佛罗多 快趴下
Frodo!
佛罗多
Where are they?
敌人在哪儿?
Let the Lord of the Black Land come forth!
岂你们黑地之王出来
Let justice be done upon him!
他该得到正义的惩罚
Fall back.
撤退
It's gone, Mr. Frodo.
没事了 佛罗多老爷
The light's passed on, away towards the north.
他的视线移过去了 转身北方
Something's drawn its gaze.
那里一定出了什么事
Hold your ground! Hold your ground.
坚持 坚持住
Sons of Gondor, of Rohan, my brothers!
罗罕国和刚铎的子孙 我的好兄弟
I see in your eyes...
在你们眼中
...the same fear that would take the heart of me.
我看到了自己内心愿有的恐惧
A day may come when the courage of Men fails...
也许有一天 人类会失去勇气
... when we forsake our friends and break all bonds of fellowship.
抛弃朋友 做出背信痉义之事
But it is not this day.
但决不会是今天
An hour of wolves and shattered shields...
也许有一天 肝狼当道 生灵涂产
... when the age of Men comes crashing down.
人类面临生死存亡
But it is not this day.
但决不会是今天
This day we fight!
今天我们该浴血奋战
By all that you hold dear on this good earth...
西方联军的勇士们
... bid you stand, Men of the West!
以你们家乡亲人的名义 命令你们战斗
Never thought I'd die fighting side by side with an Elf.
没想到我会跟精灵并肩战死
What about side by side with a friend?
那就算是和你的朋友并肩战死吧
Aye.
别
I could do that.
那还差不多
Do you remember the Shire, Mr. Frodo?
你还记得夏尔国吗 佛罗多老他
It'll be spring soon.
春天快到了
And the orchards will be in blossom.
果园里又要开满鲜花
And the birds will be nesting in the hazel thicket.
小乌在棱树从中筑千
And they'll be sowing the summer barley in the lower fields...
人们要在洼地里播种夏季大麦
...and eating the first of the strawberries with cream.
巷着奶油吃最先成熟的草草
Do you remember the taste of strawberries?
你还记得草莓的味道吗?
No, Sam.
不 山姆
I can't recall the taste of food...
我已记不起食物的味道
...nor the sound of water...
流消的水声
...nor the touch of grass.
或是青草的感觉
I'm...
我们
...naked in the dark.
身陷黑暗之地
There's-- There's nothing.
无依无靠
No veil between me and the wheel of fire.
随时会被索伦的魔腿发现
l can see him...
我看见他了
.. with my waking eyes.
好像就在眼前
Then let us be rid of it...
那咱们就把魔戒扔掉
...once and for all.
一了百了
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
来吧 佛罗多老爷
I can't carry it for you...
我不能拿魔戒
...but I can carry you.
但我可以背你
Come on!
咱们走
Aragorn.
阿拉贡
Elessar.
人类之王
For Frodo.
为了佛罗多
Look, Mr. Frodo.
看哪 佛罗多老爷
A doorway.
有一扇门
We're almost there.
我们快到了
Clever Hobbits to climb so high!
聪明的需比特人能够胎这么高
Frodo!
不 佛罗多
Eagles.
老应
The eagles are coming!
老应来了
Frodo!
佛罗多
I'm here, Sam.
我在这儿 山姆
Destroy it!
毁掉它
Go on! Now!
快点 快
Throw it in the fire!
把它扔进火里
What are you waiting for?
你还等什么
Just let it go!
快点扔下去
The Ring is mine.
魔戒是我的
No.
不
Yes!
好了啊
Precious! Precious!
宝贝 宝贝
Give me your hand!
伸出手来
Take my hand!
抓住我的手
No!
不
Don't you let go.
二万别松开
Don't let go.
别松开
Reach!
用力
Frodo!
佛罗多
It's gone.
它消失了
It's done.
成功了
Yes, Mr. Frodo.
是的 佛罗多老爷
It's over now.
彻底结束了
l can see the Shire.
我看到了夏尔国
The Brandywine River.
白兰都因河
Bag End.
我的老家
Gandalf's fireworks.
甘道夫的焰火
The lights in the Party Tree.
晚会树上挂着彩灯
Rosie Cotton dancing.
罗丝. 考顿在跳舞
She had ribbons in her hair.
头上扎着丝带
If ever 1 was to marry someone...
要是我娶媳妇
...it would've been her.
一定会要她
I'm glad to be with you, Samwise Gamgee...
真高兴有你做伴 山姆怀斯， 甘姆齐
...here at the end of all things.
这一切就要过去了
Gandalf?
甘道夫?
Frodo!
佛罗多
Now come the days of the king.
国王时代从此开始
This day does not belong to one man...
这个日子不属于某个人
...but to all.
属于所有人
Let us together rebuild this world...
让我们一起重建家园
..that we may share in the days of peace.
共享和和平幸福的了时光
My friends...
我的朋友
... you bow to no one.
朋友们 该鞠躬的是我
And thus it was.
就这样
A Fourth Age of Middle-earth began.
开始了中土世界第四纪
And the Fellowship of the Ring...
护戒队
... though eternally bound by friendship and love...
解散了
...was ended.
但永恒的友谊和爱情与世长存
Thirteen months to the day since Gandalf sent us on our long journey...
就在甘道夫派我们踏上 护戒之旅后的第13个月
...we found ourselves looking upon a familiar sight.
我们又看到了自己熟悉的景色
We were home.
我们到家了
Hey, watch the pumpkin.
小心南瓜
Rosie, Rosie.
罗丝 罗丝
Good night, lads.
晚安 小伙子们
How do you pick up the threads of an old life?
怎样才能真正回到 自己曾经熟悉的生活
How do you go on...
怎么办
...when in your heart you begin to understand...
你明明知道过去的一切
... there is no going back?
不可能回来?
There are some things that time cannot mend...
有些伤口 就连时间也难以弥合
...some hurts that go foo deep...
它们太深太深
...that have taken hold.
你永远也无法摆脱
Mr. Frodo?
佛罗多老爷?
What is it?
出了什么事
It's been four years to the day since Weathertop, Sam.
风云项上的事已经过去了4年
It's never really healed.
我的伤口还没有愈合
"There and Back Again: A Hobbit's Tale by Bilbo Baggins.
《归去来今 一个需比特人的故事》 比尔博' 巴金斯著
And The Lord of the Rings by Frodo Baggins."
《指环王》佛罗多“' 巴金斯著
You finished it.
你写完了?
Not quite.
没有
There's room for a little more.
还有一点没写完
Bilbo once told me his part in this tale would end...
比尔博曾经说他的故事讲完了
... that each of us must come and go in the telling.
还有我们这些人的故事要继续讲
Bilbo's story was now over.
比尔博的故事到了尾声
There would be no more journeys for him...
他的旅程已经走到尽头
... Save one.
还差一点
Tell me again, lad, where are we going?
再说一遍 我们这是去哪儿
To the harbor, Bilbo.
去码头 比尔博
The Elves have accorded you a special honor...
精灵人授予您一项特别荣誉
...a place on the last ship to leave Middle-earth.
让你搭乘离开中土世界的末班船
Frodo...
佛罗多
...any chance of seeing that old Ring of mine again?
能让我看看我的老戒指吗
The one I gave you.
我送你的那枚?
Sorry, Uncle.
抱歉 叔叔
I'm afraid I lost it.
我把它弄雪了
Oh.
响
Pity.
真可惜
I should like to have held it one last time.
真想再看上一眼
Well, here's a sight l have never seen before.
这种景象我还是第一次见到
The power of the Three Rings is ended.
三大魔戒气数已尽
The time has come...
人类主字的时代
...for the dominion of Men.
已经到来
I think I'm...
我想
... quite ready for another adventure.
我完全可以开始新的旅程
Farewell...
再见了
...my brave Hobbits.
勇敢的需比特人
My work is now finished.
我已经完成自己的使命
Here at last, on the shores of the sea...
今天 在这大海的岸边
...comes the end of our Fellowship.
护戒之旅将最终结束
I will not say, "Do not weep"...
我不想说“别哭”
...for not all tears are an evil.
眼泪并不全是坏事
It is time, Frodo.
时间到了 佛罗多
What does he mean?
什么意思
We set out to save the Shire, Sam.
我们出征是为了夏尔国 山姆
And it has been saved.
夏尔国得救了
But not for me.
但我不能留下
You don't mean that.
这不是真的
You can't leave.
你不能走
The last pages are for you, Sam.
最后的篇章由你续写 山姆
My dear Sam:
亲爱的山姆
You cannot always be forn in two.
我不能再分享你的挚爱
You will have to be one and whole for many years.
你应该一心一意过你自己的日子
You have so much to enjoy and to be and fo do.
你可以尽情享受快乐 享受生活 享受人生
Your part in the story will go on.
你的故事将源远流长
Well...
好了
...[m back.
我回来了